<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Sayz Lim]]></title>
  <link href="https://sayzlim.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://sayzlim.net/"/>
  <updated>2022-07-27T09:13:13+07:00</updated>
  <id>https://sayzlim.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sayz Lim]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[talk@sayzlim.net]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com">Jekyll</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Started with Obsidian]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/getting-started-obsidian/"/>
    <updated>2022-07-06T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/getting-started-obsidian</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve switched from Evernote to Obsidian because I like the idea of building a knowledge base on top of folders and Markdown files. Here are some tips to help you get started if you’re new to Obsidian.</p>

<ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#daily-notes--fleeting-notes" id="markdown-toc-daily-notes--fleeting-notes">Daily Notes / Fleeting Notes</a></li>
  <li><a href="#basic-folders-structure" id="markdown-toc-basic-folders-structure">Basic Folders Structure</a></li>
  <li><a href="#map-and-remember-essential-shortcuts" id="markdown-toc-map-and-remember-essential-shortcuts">Map and Remember Essential Shortcuts</a>    <ul>
      <li><a href="#basic-shortcuts" id="markdown-toc-basic-shortcuts">Basic Shortcuts</a></li>
      <li><a href="#navigation-shortcuts" id="markdown-toc-navigation-shortcuts">Navigation Shortcuts</a></li>
      <li><a href="#formatting-shortcuts" id="markdown-toc-formatting-shortcuts">Formatting Shortcuts</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#personalize-with-theme" id="markdown-toc-personalize-with-theme">Personalize with Theme</a></li>
  <li><a href="#obsidian-graph-view" id="markdown-toc-obsidian-graph-view">Obsidian Graph View</a></li>
  <li><a href="#essential-plugins" id="markdown-toc-essential-plugins">Essential Plugins</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="daily-notes--fleeting-notes">Daily Notes / Fleeting Notes</h2>
<p>Enable Daily Notes from the core plugins, so it creates a new note whenever you open Obsidian. Some people also refer to daily notes as fleeting notes.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2022/07/obsidian-daily-note-option.webp" alt="" title="Obsidian Daily's Note Options" /></p>

<p><strong>Set the default new note location</strong> inside the Fleeting folder to prevent it from cluttering the top directory.</p>

<p>Fleeting note is a scratchpad that lets you <strong>capture the ideas and information that resonates</strong> with you throughout the day.</p>

<p>There is no structure. There is no editing. There is no filter. You capture your best and worst ideas in this note. You will schedule a time to organize these ideas later.</p>

<h2 id="basic-folders-structure">Basic Folders Structure</h2>
<p>Now you have an outlet to capture your ideas with fleeting notes. You need to organize them every day or once a week. It’s your choice. Find what works for you.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2022/07/obsidian-folders-structure.webp" alt="" title="Obsidian Folders Structure" /></p>

<p>Keep the directory structures as simple as possible if you’re new to building a knowledge base. I recommend creating these folders:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Fleeting</strong> for fleeting notes.</li>
  <li><strong>Grow</strong> for notes you create by expanding the ideas you captured from fleeting notes.</li>
  <li><strong>Resources</strong> for any information that you wish to keep for references.</li>
</ul>

<p>It’s a simplified version of CODE (Collect, Organize, Distill, Express) concept from Building a Second Brain by Tiago Forte. The structure above allows you to start capturing notes without feeling overwhelmed by the ideas of organizing them.</p>

<h2 id="map-and-remember-essential-shortcuts">Map and Remember Essential Shortcuts</h2>
<p>You should memorize some shortcuts when you first start using Obsidian. Map them under Hotkeys options if they’re not available.</p>

<h3 id="basic-shortcuts">Basic Shortcuts</h3>
<ul>
  <li><kbd>Command-Shift-P</kbd> to open the command palette.</li>
  <li><kbd>Command-O</kbd> to open a file in the existing pane.</li>
  <li><kbd>Command-Shift-F</kbd> to search in all files.</li>
  <li><kbd>Command-G</kbd> to toggle the graph.</li>
  <li><kbd>Command-R</kbd> to toggle reading view.</li>
  <li><kbd>Command-Shift-M</kbd> to move the file to another folder.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="navigation-shortcuts">Navigation Shortcuts</h3>
<ul>
  <li><kbd>Command-Option-Arrow</kbd> to navigate note history. You can remap it to <kbd>Command-Shift-Bracket</kbd> to match browser shortcuts.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="formatting-shortcuts">Formatting Shortcuts</h3>
<p>Map the following shortcut so you can start highlighting notes.</p>
<ul>
  <li><kbd>Command-L</kbd> to highlight notes.</li>
</ul>

<p>You can learn more about <a href="https://help.obsidian.md/How+to/Format+your+notes">formatting your notes</a> from the official guide.</p>

<h2 id="personalize-with-theme">Personalize with Theme</h2>
<p>Obsidian comes up with many beautiful community themes. Browse the collection and choose the one that showcases your personality.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2022/07/obsidian-theme-option.webp" alt="" title="Theme Selection in Obsidian" /></p>

<h2 id="obsidian-graph-view">Obsidian Graph View</h2>
<p>Graph View is useless initially if you’re new to building a knowledge base with Obsidian. It becomes more valuable as you continue making notes’ connections through WikiLinks and tags. It takes time to see the benefit of Graph View. Pick one note-taking method to build these connections — I personally use <a href="https://zettelkasten.de/posts/overview/">Zettelkasten Method</a>.</p>

<h2 id="essential-plugins">Essential Plugins</h2>
<p>There are two types of plugins. Core plugins are available in Obsidian by default. Community plugins are built by the community. You need to install them before you can use them. I don’t recommend adding too many community plugins because it may slow down Obsidian.</p>

<p>Here are some core plugins you should enable.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Daily notes — Create and open today’s daily note.</li>
  <li>Tag pane — Display your tags and their number of occurrences.</li>
  <li>Backlinks — Show links from other files to this file.</li>
</ul>

<p>You can click Browse from the community plugins options page to install community plugins. Here are some community plugins that you should consider installing.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Typewriter Scroll — It keeps the cursor centered in the editor view.</li>
  <li>Dynamic Table of Contents — Generates Table of Contents based on the document’s headings. I use this in the beginning when I capture long-form for notes.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Repeat Actions and Macros in Keyboard Maestro]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/loop-repeat-macros-keyboard-maestro/"/>
    <updated>2022-07-01T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/loop-repeat-macros-keyboard-maestro</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There are several ways to repeat macro and actions in Keyboard Maestro, and the method is different depending on your use case. I’m going to cover my favorite method in this post.</p>

<p>Three main actions that can help you repeat a macro in Keyboard Maestro.</p>
<ul>
  <li>Repeat — Repeat a macro for a specified number amount of times.</li>
  <li>Until — Repeat a macro <strong>until</strong> it meets a specified condition.</li>
  <li>While — Repeat a macro <strong>while</strong> it meets a specified condition.</li>
</ul>

<p>Most of the time, you only need to use <strong>repeat</strong> action to loop over the macros. The main advantage is that it allows you to decide how many times you want to run them and save yourself from dealing with the uncertainty of checking variables in Until and While actions.<sup id="fnref:20220701083325" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:20220701083325" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>For example, sometimes, I need to get the SimilarWeb stats from the websites I found. I put these data in a spreadsheet and enter the number of times I want to repeat the macro that pulls the required information.</p>

<p>Here is the macro that shows you how it works.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2022/07/keyboard-maestro-repeat-action.webp" alt="" title="Keyboard Maestro Repeat Action" /></p>

<p>Create an action that prompts input from you to enter the number of times you want to repeat a group of actions or a macro. Save to a variable called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">LocalRepeatAmount</code>.</p>

<p>Create another action that repeats the actions based on the value of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">LocalRepeatAmount</code>. The combination of repeat action and local variable lets you choose how many times you want to run the macro instead of going back into the editor to update the number of times to run the macro.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:20220701083325" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>These two actions are more suitable when you want to check the environment and screen conditions before you resume actions in a macro. <a href="#fnref:20220701083325" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prioritize Health]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/prioritize-health/"/>
    <updated>2022-06-16T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/prioritize-health</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the last eight years, I’ve made a lot of decisions. There were some good and bad choices, but I always end up in a better situation if I follow this one rule.</p>

<p>Health comes first.</p>

<p>I am able to perform and think more effectively in both life and work when I make decisions that benefit my physical and mental health. I can sit without worrying about my back hurting. I can stay focused longer. I can think and analyze without feeling anxious.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/sayzlim/status/1535493652998500353">My goal</a> is to be a good parent to my children. I want to be there whenever they need me. I want to be able to carry them upstairs without hurting my knees. I want to provide for them until they are old enough to care for themselves.</p>

<p>Most people glorifying hustle culture fail to take care of their health. Even before I became a parent, I prioritized my health by <em>trying</em> to have a balanced diet and exercise regularly.</p>

<p>If you are given the option, <strong>always choose to be healthy.</strong></p>

<p>If there is one productivity tip I want to share with you, it is to keep yourself healthy so that you can do the work you’re proud of in the next two decades.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Better "Quit All" with Keyboard Maestro]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/better-quit-all/"/>
    <updated>2022-06-04T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/better-quit-all</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When I’m done with the work, I enter “quitall” with Alfred and quit all the apps in the Dock. I found out that I need more control to decide which apps to keep active.</p>

<p>I’ve been using Alfred built-in <strong>Quit All</strong> to quit all the applications whenever I’m done with my work. It’s a great way to end the day so you can see a clean working space.</p>

<p>However, there are some apps that I want to keep active in the Dock such as Timemator for time tracking and Drafts for note-taking. Unfortunately, Alfred doesn’t have a built-in option to exclude apps from this command.</p>

<p>Which brings me to Keyboard Maestro.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2022/06/keyboard-maestro-preferences.webp" alt="" title="Keyboard Maestro Excluded Preferences" /></p>

<p><strong>Keyboard Maestro offers more flexibility</strong> when it comes to building a macro that caters to your needs. All you need to do is to add the apps you want to exclude from the preferences and the app will take care of the rest.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2022/06/alfred-quitall-command.webp" alt="" title="Alfred Custom 'Quit All' Command" /></p>

<p>The next thing you want to do is to create a search command in Alfred that runs <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/usr/bin/osascript (AppleScript)</code>. You can paste the script below to tell Keyboard Maestro Engine to execute the</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>-- The passed query is the UUID of the macro
tell application "Keyboard Maestro Engine"
  do script "5F2B4E32-239D-4B46-BA07-2F0F103CE1EA"
end tell
</code></pre></div></div>

<p><img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2022/06/keyboard-maestro-copy-uuid.webp" alt="" title="Copy Macro UUID in Keyboard Maestro" /></p>

<p>You can get the UUID of a macro by right-clicking and selecting <strong>Copy as UUID</strong> from the contextual menu. For example, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">5F2B4E32-239D-4B46-BA07-2F0F103CE1EA</code> is the UUID for the Quit All macro in my library.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Text Expansion with Keyboard Maestro]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/text-expansion-keyboard-maestro/"/>
    <updated>2022-05-19T07:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/text-expansion-keyboard-maestro</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I replaced TextExpander with Keyboard Maestro as my primary text expansion tool because I prefer the native editing experience and the flexibility that Keyboard Maestro offers.</p>

<p>The post on <a href="/memorable-textexpander-abbreviations/" title="Creating Memorable TextExpander Abbreviations - Sayz Lim">creating memorable abbreviations</a> is still relevant regardless of what apps you use for this task. In this post, I’m going to share some tips and changes I’ve made to import the snippets that I often use in TextExpander.</p>

<h2 id="organize-them-with-emoji">Organize Them with Emoji</h2>
<p>By default, Keyboard Maestro sorts macro groups by name. The only way to categorize similar macro groups together is by prepending the group name with a symbol or an emoji — I wrote a post that covers more details on <a href="/organize-keyboard-maestro-macros/" title="How I Organize Keyboard Maestro Macro Groups - Sayz Lim">organizing your library separately</a>.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2022/05/keyboard-maestro-text-expansion.webp" alt="" title="Organize Keyboard Maestro Groups with Emoji" /></p>

<p>I have more than ten snippet groups in TextExpander. However, I’ve decided to import two snippet groups that I often use and prepend them with “Media Shuffle Playback” emoji 🔀 which is kind of similar to expanding.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>🔀 Avoid These Words</strong>: This group contains the word that I want to avoid and correct. It also omits some useless words like <strong>basically</strong>, <strong>actually</strong>, and <strong>clearly</strong>.</li>
  <li><strong>🔀 Text Expansion (or General)</strong>: This group acts as a general group for my most frequently used snippets. I might move some of them to their dedicated group later on.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="prompt-for-user-input">Prompt for User Input</h2>
<p>One of the key features that make TextExpander great is its wide selection of fill-in fields that allows you to complete the missing snippet details on the fly.</p>

<p>Here’s an example of this kind of snippet:</p>

<div class="language-md highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Hi <span class="nt">&lt;FirstName&gt;</span>,

I'm from <span class="nt">&lt;AgencyName&gt;</span> which specializes in helping offline business grow their online presence through social media and website branding.

I researched about <span class="nt">&lt;LeadCompany&gt;</span> and want to share some tips to help you gain more customers:

{ list the reasons }

Are you available for a quick call to discuss this partnership?
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>You can request all these details with Prompt for User Input action and save them to local variables before expanding them. Here is what it looks like in Keyboard Maestro.</p>

<p class="sidenote">Prepending <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Local</code> to the variable name will make it available only to the macro calling it. <a href="https://wiki.keyboardmaestro.com/manual/Variables" title="Keyboard Maestro Variables">Learn more here</a>.</p>

<div class="language-md highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>Hi %Variable%LocalFirstName%,

I'm from %Variable%LocalAgencyName% which specializes in helping offline business grow their online presence through social media and website branding.

I researched about %Variable%LocalLeadCompany% and want to share some tips to help you gain more customers:

{ list the reasons }

Are you available for a quick call to discuss this partnership?
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="prompt-with-list-from-text">Prompt with List from Text</h2>
<p>Here is a simple macro that you can create that lets you choose which email address to use. By assigning <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@@@</code> as the abbreviation, you can enter your email addresses as a list that you can choose whenever you need them.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2022/05/keyboard-maestro-email.webp" alt="" title="Keyboard Maestro Prompt with List from Text" /></p>

<p>You can enter your personal email address and work email address in this macro. Another example use case is whenever I write an email template that offers different questions or options. Instead of writing them down whenever there is a prompt, you can save them into a list and select them with a filter.</p>

<h2 id="format-with-icudatetime">Format with ICUDateTime</h2>
<p>I have a specific use case where I expand <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.now</code> into today’s date. It’s nothing fancy. I use them to prepend my notes and files that should be sorted by date in the file system.</p>

<p>By combining it with Prompt with List from Text action, I set up a shortcut for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">.pay</code> that lets me name the note I send to my Evernote’s Receipts notebook.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>%ICUDateTime%yyyy-MM-dd% %Variable%LocalClipboard%
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="insert-by-pasting-vs-insert-by-typing">Insert by Pasting vs Insert by Typing</h2>
<p><strong>Insert by Pasting offers better performance</strong> because it doesn’t need to simulate any keystrokes. However, you will encounter some scenarios where using Insert by Typing is an ideal choice. Here are some of those scenarios:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Some websites prevent you from pasting from your clipboard into their email/password field.</li>
  <li>You want to maintain the focus of the dialog/input window from applications like Alfred or Spotlight.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HubSpot Deployment Shell Script]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/hubspot-deployment-shell-script/"/>
    <updated>2022-05-14T09:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/hubspot-deployment-shell-script</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started building and managing websites with HubSpot recently because it offers the flexibility to allow other team members, especially those who are in the marketing team, to create and customize a landing page.</p>

<p>Instead of following recommended deployment method by HubSpot, I need to find a way to make the development process seamless while also allowing the rest of the team members to make changes in the Design Tools. It means that the rest of the team members don’t have to use version control if they prefer to update the code directly.</p>

<p>I decided to write a shell script that allows me to choose which folder to fetch, upload, and watch. Here is the content of the shell script:</p>

<div class="language-zsh highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c">#!/usr/bin/env zsh</span>

<span class="c"># List of projects in their respective folder</span>
<span class="c"># "folder_paths" is a dictionary, you can add more folders</span>
<span class="c"># if you need to specify a different project to watch.</span>
<span class="nb">declare</span> <span class="nt">-A</span> folder_paths

folder_paths[root]<span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"Default/"</span>
folder_paths[carbon]<span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"Templates/Carbon/"</span>
folder_paths[publishers]<span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"Templates/Publishers/"</span>

<span class="c"># Default Options</span>
<span class="nv">portal</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">portal</span><span class="k">:-</span><span class="nv">DEV</span><span class="k">}</span>
<span class="nv">project</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">project</span><span class="k">:-</span><span class="nv">root</span><span class="k">}</span>
<span class="nv">action</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">action</span><span class="k">:-</span><span class="nv">watch</span><span class="k">}</span>

<span class="k">while</span> <span class="o">[</span> <span class="nv">$# </span><span class="nt">-gt</span> 0 <span class="o">]</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">do
   if</span> <span class="o">[[</span> <span class="nv">$1</span> <span class="o">==</span> <span class="k">*</span><span class="s2">"--"</span><span class="k">*</span> <span class="o">]]</span><span class="p">;</span> <span class="k">then
        </span><span class="nv">param</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">1</span><span class="p">/--/</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span>
        <span class="nb">declare</span> <span class="nv">$param</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="nv">$2</span><span class="s2">"</span>
        <span class="c"># echo $1 $2 // Optional to see the parameter:value result</span>
   <span class="k">fi
  </span><span class="nb">shift
</span><span class="k">done</span>

<span class="c"># Main Commands</span>
<span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"[Working Portal] : </span><span class="se">\"</span><span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">portal</span><span class="k">}</span> <span class="s2">"portal"</span><span class="se">\"</span>
<span class="nb">echo</span> <span class="s2">"[Selected Folder] : </span><span class="se">\"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">folder_paths</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">project</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="se">\"</span><span class="s2">"</span>
hs <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">action</span><span class="k">}</span> <span class="nt">--account</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">portal</span><span class="k">}</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">folder_paths</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">project</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span> <span class="s2">"</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">folder_paths</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">project</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="p">]</span><span class="k">}</span><span class="s2">"</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="how-it-works">How It Works</h2>
<p>For example, if I need to upload the changes I made to the Carbon website, I can run this command:</p>

<div class="language-zsh highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>zsh deploy.sh <span class="nt">--action</span> upload <span class="nt">--portal</span> PROD <span class="nt">--project</span> carbon
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The available commands are based on <a href="https://developers.hubspot.com/docs/cms/developer-reference/local-development-cli" title="Local Development Tooling: CLI Reference">HubSpot CLI</a>. You can also run other commands such as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--action watch</code> if you wish to watch and preview the changes you’ve made locally on the staging or production.</p>

<p>I want to share why this shell script is important in the daily workflow. When it comes to the business, we need to be able to prioritize. If you’re like me, you probably want to follow the best practice to deploy changes to the production website. However, there are other factors to take into consideration.</p>

<ul>
  <li>The team members must be able to make changes using HubSpot Design Tools without waiting for developers.</li>
  <li>Developers must be able to use keep the version history of the changes they’ve made to the project.</li>
  <li>Several developers should still be able to collaborate through the shared remote repository.</li>
</ul>

<p>Although it’s ideal to set up Continuous Integration with the GitHub repository, I feel that creating a simple shell script above can accommodate the current needs of the business where we need the flexibility from both marketers and developers to push updates quickly.</p>

<p>One thing I’ve learned from being on the side of “not” working with codes and working with codes directly is to choose the most efficient and resilient method when it comes to solving a problem.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tips to Maintain a Forked Repository]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/tips-maintain-forked-repository/"/>
    <updated>2021-09-13T17:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/tips-maintain-forked-repository</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Working with <a href="https://www.carbonads.net" title="Carbon Ads">Carbon</a> means I have to fork some open-source projects to submit a pull request with the ad code integration. Here is the list of the tips I’ve collected while learning how to contribute to the public repositories.</p>

<p>By forking a repository, it means that you’ve cloned an identical project that you can edit. Whenever you make a mistake, the worst-case scenario is to delete the forked repository and clone it again.</p>

<p>The main purpose of these tips is to <strong>avoid resetting the repository</strong> and understand the workflow to contribute back to the upstream project.</p>

<p class="sidenote">I will be referring to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">master</code> branch as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main</code> in this post. They can be used interchangeably, but most new projects prefer to name their default branch as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main</code>.</p>

<h2 id="always-create-a-new-branch">Always Create a New Branch</h2>
<p>Branching is a safe way for you to experiment with a new feature without affecting the main branch. Even if you’re making a minor update to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">README</code>, you’re still going to create a new branch because it will keep the main branch clean.</p>

<p>Whenever you’re done with a feature, you can push the branch you’re working to your forked repository. Then, you can follow up by submitting a pull request to the upstream.</p>

<p class="sidenote">The <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">upstream</code> remote refers to <strong>the original source</strong> of your forked repository. You can check the configured remote repository by running <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git remote -v</code> in Terminal. <a href="https://docs.github.com/en/github/collaborating-with-pull-requests/working-with-forks/configuring-a-remote-for-a-fork" title="Configuring a remote for a fork - GitHub Docs">Follow this guide by GitHub</a> to configure remote repository.</p>

<h2 id="never-commit-to-the-main-branch">Never Commit to the Main Branch</h2>
<p>You should never commit to the main branch. I mentioned before that we want to keep the main branch clean. What exactly do we want to keep it clean from?</p>

<p>We don’t want our local commits in the main branch.</p>

<p>The local main branch should always match to the upstream origin. Adding commits to the local main branch will create conflicts that trigger Git to asks you merge, rebase, or fast-forward the tree history.</p>

<p>Instead of committing to the main branch, you want the upstream maintainer to accept your pull request, and then you can match the HEAD of your main branch to the upstream main branch. Here’s the command you can run:</p>

<div class="language-console highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="go">git switch main
git pull upstream main --ff
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<p>Let’s run through each line. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git switch main</code> lets you switch to the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main</code> branch where you can apply the update from the upstream. Once you’re on the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main</code> branch, you can pull the latest update and pass <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--ff</code> option to fast forward the commits. It’s optional to pass <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">--ff</code> if you keep the main branch clean, however, it’s a good practice to always decide how you want to deal with the conflicts.</p>

<h2 id="dealing-with-conflicts-on-main-branch">Dealing with Conflicts on Main Branch</h2>
<p>I often messed up the main branch when I was learning using Git. The most common mistake is to run this command on the main branch.</p>

<div class="language-console highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="go">git pull upstream main
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<p>Here is the problem with the command above.</p>

<p>You’re telling git to fetch and update the active branch to match the remote branch <strong>without specifying how you want to deal with the conflicts</strong>.</p>

<p>Then this happens:</p>
<ol>
  <li>I panicked because I didn’t know how to deal with the conflicts.</li>
  <li>I gave up, deleted the folder, and recloned the remote repository.</li>
</ol>

<p>There is no need to panic because you’re still working on your local and remote branch.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> The worst-case scenario is to delete and refork the repository if you’re still unfamiliar with Git.</p>

<p>However, you can easily fix this issue by running this command:</p>

<div class="language-console highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="go">git reflog
git reset HEAD@{index}
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<p>Let’s break down the command above.</p>

<ul>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">reflog</code> shows the history of updates that happened to the tip of branches in the local repository.</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git reset HEAD@{index}</code> reset the branch to the number of moves based on the passed <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">index</code> value. <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">HEAD@{index}</code> is one of many ways to specify revision value. I personally prefer to use the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sha1</code> value.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="syncing-local-main-branch-to-upstream">Syncing Local Main Branch to Upstream</h2>
<p>You can deal with most conflicts locally before submitting a pull request. The reason is the upstream main branch might have received more commits since the last time you cloned it. Match the tip of your local main branch to the upstream main branch. Here’s what you can run:</p>

<div class="language-console highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="go">git fetch upstream main
git switch main &amp;&amp; rebase upstream/main
git push origin main
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="pushing-force-to-remote-branch">Pushing –Force to Remote Branch</h2>
<p>Sometimes I want to set things right for both local and remote repository. I don’t plan to keep any updates I’ve made and my main goal is to sync local and remote repository to restart everything.</p>

<p class="sidenote"><strong>You can only do this if you’re the only one who manage repository</strong>. For example, I can do it for my Jekyll site because the repository is private and no one else will be affected if I forcibly push an update to the remote repository.</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>git reflog
git reset --hard &lt;sha1-value&gt;
git branch -r
git fetch upstream main &amp;&amp; git rebase upstream/main
git push --force origin main
</code></pre></div></div>

<ol>
  <li>Check for the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sha1</code> value we’re going to pass into the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git reset</code> command.</li>
  <li>Reset the branch before it’s broken.</li>
  <li>List all remote repositories with their branches. Most of the time, you’re looking at the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">upstream/main</code> branch.</li>
  <li>Fetch the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main</code> branch from <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">upstream</code> and rebase local <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main</code> branch to the upstream <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main</code> branch.</li>
  <li>Push local <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">main</code> branch to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">origin/main</code> remote branch.</li>
</ol>

<p>This step will ensure you have a clean slate of a local and remote main branch without deleting the forked repository. Next, create and start your work from the new branch.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Unless you’re working in a company that allows you to push your commit to the remote main branch. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Fix 'jekyll-autoprefixer' Error Running Ruby 3.0.0]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/fix-jekyll-autoprefixer-error/"/>
    <updated>2021-07-15T15:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/fix-jekyll-autoprefixer-error</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I postponed upgrading my Ruby environment to 3.x.x for a while because I couldn’t build or serve this Jekyll site due to the error with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jekyll-autoprefixer</code>.</p>

<p>Here is the error I encountered when I tried to build this site.</p>

<div class="language-console highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="go">TypeError: Cannot read property 'version' of undefined (ExecJS::ProgramError)
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<p class="sidenote">I assume you’re using <a href="https://bundler.io/" title="Bundler: The best way to manage a Ruby application's gems">Bundler</a> to manage the gems. If you’re not familiar with Bundler, I recommend that you check it out and use it to set up dependencies for your project.</p>

<p>You can fix the error by downgrading <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">execjs</code> back to 2.7.0.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Add the following line <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">gem 'execjs', '2.7.0'</code> to your Gemfile.</p>

<p>Then run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">bundle update</code> to update all the installed gems.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>You can <a href="https://github.com/vwochnik/jekyll-autoprefixer/issues/11" title="ExecJS 2.8.0 breaks Jekyll">check out this issue</a> to see a different method to fix it. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Verify 'osxkeychain helper' Personal Access Token]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/verify-osxkeychain-helper/"/>
    <updated>2021-07-10T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/verify-osxkeychain-helper</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I like using GitHub for macOS because it lets me compare the difference of files before each commit. If you’ve configured credential helper to <a href="https://docs.github.com/en/get-started/getting-started-with-git/caching-your-github-credentials-in-git" title="Caching your GitHub credentials in Git - GitHub Docs">tell Git to remember your password</a>, you also want to learn how to verify that the personal access token has been stored correctly.</p>

<p>The official application uses HTTPS as the default protocol, so I have to enter the password every time I want to push the update in Terminal. Caching the credentials allows me to continue using HTTPS as the protocol while offering the flexibility to push the updates through the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git</code> command.</p>

<p><a href="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/07/osxkeychain-helper.webp" title="GitHub Personall Access Token in macOS Keychain Access"> <img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/07/osxkeychain-helper.webp" alt="GitHub Personall Access Token in macOS Keychain Access" title="GitHub Personall Access Token in macOS Keychain Access" /> </a></p>

<p>Here’s how you can verify that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">osxkeychain helper</code> is storing your personal access token.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Open Keychain Access with Spotlight</li>
  <li>Search for <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">github.com</code> — it will show up as an “Internet password”</li>
  <li>Double-click on the item to view the attributes</li>
  <li>Click “Show password” and enter your macOS account password to view the access token</li>
  <li>Open “Access Control” to verify that <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">git credential-osxkeychain</code> CLI is the only one that can access this item</li>
</ol>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Self-Host Plausible with Amazon EC2 Free Tier]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/self-host-plausible-amazon-ec2/"/>
    <updated>2021-07-04T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/self-host-plausible-amazon-ec2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I decided to self-host Plausible because I want to keep the cost of maintaining this site as low as possible. So here are some resources to help you configure Plausible for free on Amazon EC2.</p>

<p><a href="https://plausible.io/" title="Plausible Analytics - Simple, privacy-friendly alternative to Google Analytics">Plausible</a> is lightweight and privacy-friendly analytics for people who want to see only the essential stats of their site.</p>

<p>If you’re not concerned with the pricing, you can subscribe to their basic plan for $6/month and track the page views up to 10k per month. Choosing this option means you can focus on growing your projects and spend less time managing the server running Plausible.</p>

<p>The main advantage of self-hosting Plausible is the cost. You can eliminate the cost of analytics by creating a virtual machine on the cloud. Thanks to the folks at Plausible for making the project open-source; you can easily create a free instance on Amazon EC2 and get Plausible running in hours.</p>

<h2 id="getting-started-with-amazon-ec2">Getting Started with Amazon EC2</h2>
<p><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/ec2/" title="Amazon EC2">Amazon EC2</a> is a web service that lets you create virtual machines (known as instances) in the cloud. They’re also known as <strong>Cloud Server</strong>.</p>

<p>Other cloud servers also offer free-tier, but I’m going to use Amazon EC2 because I’ve already used Amazon S3 for my static documents. Sign in with your Amazon account to access the dashboard.</p>

<p>Follow these steps to create a new instance that we will use to set up Plausible.</p>
<ol>
  <li>Select “Instances” from the sidebar</li>
  <li>Select “Launch Instances”</li>
  <li>Enable “Free-tier only” filter in the sidebar</li>
  <li>Choose Ubuntu Server 20.04 LTS (HVM) 64-bit (x86)</li>
  <li>Choose the free tier option in the list</li>
  <li>Select “Review and Launch” to complete the instance setup</li>
  <li>Save the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PEM</code> certificate somewhere safe</li>
</ol>

<p>You’ll be asked to name the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PEM</code> certificate. I name the certificate as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">aws-ubuntu</code> and save it in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">~/.ssh</code> directory. <strong>Keep the certificate safe</strong> because you will need it whenever you want to access the server.</p>

<p>Before connecting to the instance you’ve just created, you need to set the inbound security rules to accept requests made to port 80 and 443. You can click on the running instance and select the <strong>Security</strong> tab under the instance summary. Next, click on the security groups and set the following inbound rules.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Type</th>
      <th>Protocol</th>
      <th>Port range</th>
      <th>Source</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>HTTP</td>
      <td>TCP</td>
      <td>80</td>
      <td>0.0.0.0/0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SSH</td>
      <td>TCP</td>
      <td>22</td>
      <td>0.0.0.0/0</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>HTTPS</td>
      <td>TCP</td>
      <td>443</td>
      <td>0.0.0.0/0</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="connecting-instance-through-ssh">Connecting Instance Through SSH</h2>
<p><strong>Make sure you can connect to the instance through SSH.</strong> You can follow the instructions under the “Connect” tab to get started. I personally use macOS built-in Terminal application to access the remote server.</p>

<p>Here’s a command you enter into Terminal with the information you copied from the “Connect” tab.</p>

<div class="language-console highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="go">ssh -i "aws-ubuntu.pem" ubuntu@ec2-1-111-222-33.us-east-2.compute.amazonaws.com
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<p class="sidenote">The command you want to paste will look different from the one you see above. Pay attention to the name of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">PEM</code> certificate and the remote address to access your server.</p>

<h2 id="notes-on-setting-up-plausible">Notes on Setting Up Plausible</h2>
<p>Tyler has written a <a href="https://tinkerlog.dev/journal/self-hosting-analytics-with-plausible-and-nginx-on-ubuntu-server" title="Self hosting analytics with Plausible &amp; NGINX on Ubuntu Server | Tinker log">concise tutorial to help you setting up Plausible on a Ubuntu Server</a>. You should be able to get Plausible running if you follow each step carefully.</p>

<p>Here are some notes you want to pay attention to when setting up Plausible.</p>

<p class="sidenote">Executing commands as a root user is not exactly a best practice when it comes to managing a remote server. You usually want to set up a separate user account under the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">sudo</code> group. However, for a personal project like this, you can skip creating a user account if you’re not comfortable with accounts management.</p>

<p><strong>Public IPv4 address</strong> is the IP address you want to set up as A record under the DNS configuration. For example, I access my dashboard from stats.sayzlim.net, so I will have to set the A record to point to my server’s public IP address. Make sure to set the proxy status to DNS only if you’re on CloudFlare.</p>

<p>Add <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">DISABLE_REGISTRATION=true</code> to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">plausible-conf.ev</code> file to prevent people signing up a new account on your self-hosted Plausible.</p>

<p>Run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">docker ps</code> to list all the active containers. Plausible will only work if those four containers are running. I spent hours debugging because I entered a wrong secret key. It turned out one of the containers will not run if the key length is not <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Base64</code>.</p>

<div class="language-console highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="go">hosting_plausible_1
hosting_plausible_events_db_1
hosting_mail_1
hosting_plausible_db_1
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<p>Be patient when setting up SSL certificates with certbot. Verify that the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">server_name</code> in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/etc/nginx/sites-enabled/plausible</code> has been set to the correct URL. You can verify the A record by running the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nslookup</code> command. For example, I will run <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">nslookup stats.sayzlim.net</code> and expect the public IP address in the result.</p>

<div class="language-console highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="go">Server:		192.168.1.1
</span><span class="gp">Address:	192.168.1.1#</span>53
<span class="go">
Non-authoritative answer:
Name:	stats.sayzlim.net
Address: 3.143.214.18
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<p>Send me a Twitter DM if you encounter any problems while trying to get Plausible configured on Amazon EC2. Also, make sure to <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/plausible" title="Sponsor @plausible on GitHub Sponsors · GitHub">sponsor Plausible</a> if you’ve successfully self-hosted it on your server.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Using Feedbin in 2021]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/using-feedbin/"/>
    <updated>2021-06-01T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/using-feedbin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I found out today that I’ve been using Feedbin for seven years. Feedbin started as a simple feed reader, which I used to sync over to third-party RSS clients such as <a href="https://www.reederapp.com/" title="Reeder 5">Reeder</a> and <a href="https://www.goldenhillsoftware.com/unread/" title="Unread: An RSS Reader">Unread</a>. These days, I read everything on Feedbin.</p>

<p><a href="https://feedbin.com/" title="Feedbin">Feedbin</a> added many features while I was away from my daily reading. Here are some of the features that changed the way I use Feedbin.</p>

<h3 id="send-to-feedbin-bookmarklet">Send to Feedbin Bookmarklet</h3>
<p>I used to assign my <strong>Read Later</strong> and <strong>RSS Subscription</strong> into two services: Instapaper and Feedbin.</p>

<p><a href="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/06/feedbin-bookmarklet.webp" title="Send to Feedbin Bookmarklet"> <img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/06/feedbin-bookmarklet.webp" alt="Send to Feedbin Bookmarklet" title="Send to Feedbin Bookmarklet" /> </a></p>

<p>Instapaper has a bookmarklet known as <strong>Save to Instapaper</strong> that you can put in the <strong>Favorites Bar</strong> to save articles conveniently. I will save any noteworthy articles to Instapaper and archive the read items to a notebook called <a href="https://sayzlim.net/evernote-histories/" title="Inside Evernote Histories Notebook - Sayz Lim"><strong>Histories</strong> in Evernote</a>.</p>

<p>Although I enjoy both services, I find that switching between applications for one purpose — reading and saving interesting ideas — is a distraction.</p>

<p><strong>Send to Feedbin</strong> works like <strong>Save to Instapaper</strong> by letting you send any articles to the “Pages” folder in Feedbin. By having all the subscriptions and saved articles in a single location, I can maintain the same reading experience everywhere.</p>

<p>Feedbin also does a terrific job in parsing the article with excellent integration to Evernote, where you can save these items in the semantic structure.</p>

<h3 id="recently-read">Recently Read</h3>
<p>I’m surprised that this folder is not available by default on most feed readers. I’m the type of person who tends to accidentally mark an item, so having this little folder to show my recently read items makes it easy to revisit any read items that I forgot to save to Evernote.</p>

<p><a href="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/06/feedbin-main.webp" title="Feedbin Home"> <img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/06/feedbin-main.webp" alt="Feedbin Home" title="Feedbin Home" /> </a></p>

<h3 id="actions-and-smart-filters">Actions and Smart Filters</h3>
<p>If you subscribe to popular sites that publish many articles per week, you can choose to receive notification only when the article contains a particular keyword.</p>

<p>You can achieve the setup above with <strong>Feedbin Actions</strong>.</p>

<p>You can choose to receive Push Notification if the article contains “iPhone” in the body or mark the article as read when it has [Sponsor] in the title.<sup id="fnref:2021060282957" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2021060282957" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<h3 id="subscribe-to-newsletters">Subscribe to Newsletters</h3>
<p>I gave up on Evernote when they stopped offering email forwarding unless you’re on the <strong>Premium Plan</strong>. Fortunately, Feedbin added this feature when I started actively using it again.</p>

<p>When you signed up for Feedbin, you will receive an email address that you can use to subscribe to newsletters. Every incoming email will be assigned with a tag you configured in the settings.<sup id="fnref:2021060282938" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2021060282938" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>Having Feedbin manage my newsletters means I can leave my inbox for low-volume emails.</p>

<p><strong>Avoid using Feedbin email address to subscribe to newsletters</strong>. It will be difficult to update your subscription if you decide to stop using Feedbin one day. Instead, you want to take advantage of Gmail plus notation and create a smart rule to forward incoming emails to Feedbin. For example, I will subscribe to a newsletter with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">email+feedbin@gmail.com</code> and ask Gmail to forward the emails to <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">randomGeneratedNumbers@newsletters.feedbin.com</code></p>

<p>Another thing I like about keeping newsletters in Feedbin means I can save these newsletters to Evernote for safekeeping with a simple shortcut.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:2021060282957" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I don’t recommend marking sponsored posts as read if you wish to support your favorite bloggers. <a href="#fnref:2021060282957" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2021060282938" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>The obvious tag to use in the settings is “Newsletter”. <a href="#fnref:2021060282938" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Better Way to Set Default Application on macOS]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/set-default-apps-mac/"/>
    <updated>2021-05-20T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/set-default-apps-mac</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Have you ever found that setting default application for documents on macOS is an annoying experience? It’s difficult to find out which documents that you’ve modified before. I will show you a better way to set the default application.</p>

<p>Here is the standard workflow to set the default application on Mac.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Select the document with the file extension that you want to update. For example, if you’re going to open <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">txt</code> document with iA Writer as the default application, you will want to select the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">txt</code> document in Finder.</li>
  <li>Get the document’s info by pressing <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Command - I</code> or right-click and select <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Get Info</code>.</li>
  <li>Expand the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Open with:</code> section and choose iA Writer from the list.</li>
  <li>Click <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Change All</code> to set iA Writer as the default application for all documents with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">txt</code> as the extension.</li>
</ol>

<p>It’s a straightforward process, but you won’t be able to tell which document that you’ve modified before. You’re also limited to only one default application per document type. Most people use more than one text and image editing application. You want to be able to select the default application based on the rules you’ve created.</p>

<h2 id="set-default-application-with-openin">Set Default Application with OpenIn</h2>
<p><a href="https://loshadki.app/openin/" title="OpenIn - Loshadki Apps">OpenIn</a> is a new application I discovered while I was searching for <a href="https://sayzlim.net/customize-default-apps-magic-launch/" title="Customize Default Apps with Magic Launch - Sayz Lim">Magic Launch</a> replacement. Unfortunately, Magic Launch doesn’t receive any more updates because they’ve built an application that takes advantage of the macOS native UI framework to create rules.</p>

<p>Since I’m familiar with Magic Launch, I will compare many aspects of OpenIn to Magic Launch.</p>

<p>When you first open OpenIn, you can set the default browser and mail apps in their respective preference window.</p>

<p><a href="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/05/openin-settings.webp" title="OpenIn Settings"> <img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/05/openin-settings.webp" alt="OpenIn Settings" title="OpenIn Settings" /> </a></p>

<p>It’s convenient to set the default application on macOS with OpenIn. Under the <strong>File types</strong>, you can add the document type to view all the applications that can open the associated document. For example, I’ve added <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">jpg</code> document type, and it shows me the list of applications that support this document type. I’ve also used the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Quick Actions</code> to disable all the applications and enable Pixelmator Pro, Sketch, and CleanShot X.</p>

<h2 id="opening-document-with-openin">Opening Document with OpenIn</h2>
<p>OpenIn has implemented a quick method for people to choose which application to open when several applications are set as default. It will present a list of applications that can be selected with a mouse cursor or number shortcut.</p>

<p><a href="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/05/openin-preview.gif" title="Opening Documents with OpenIn"> <img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/05/openin-preview.gif" alt="Opening Documents with OpenIn" title="Opening Documents with OpenIn" /> </a></p>

<p>There are also advanced preferences that you can set with OpenIn. Here is one area where OpenIn design direction pales compared to Magic Launch. Instead of opting to the <a href="https://developer.apple.com/design/human-interface-guidelines/macos/fields-and-labels/search-fields/" title="Search Fields - Fields and Labels - macOS - Human Interface Guidelines - Apple Developer">scope bars</a> to let us set rules for each file type, OpenIn presents the options in the sidebar. It exposes unnecessary information and makes it difficult to find which rules we’ve configured.</p>

<p>One of the most used options is probably <strong>Path Rules</strong> to enter a rule to match the document with the directory. It’s not the most intuitive way to create a rule, so I hope the developer will consider changing it to scope bars-based rules creation.</p>

<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>OpenIn has made managing default applications for each document much more manageable. If you’re looking for a more granular way to set default applications, you’re going to like what OpenIn offers. You can purchase OpenIn for $9.99, or you can get it on Setapp by <a href="http://sayzlim.net/go/setapp/" title="Sign Up Setapp">signing up for a 7-days trial</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Build a Jekyll Component]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/jekyll-include-component/"/>
    <updated>2021-05-07T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/jekyll-include-component</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Jekyll is a static site generator with some great ideas to help us structure a website. By taking advantage of some of these ideas, you can decouple the complicated part of the project and build them as separate components.</p>

<p>Jekyll provides a tag called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">include</code>, which you can use to include content from other documents. Using the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">include</code> tag, you can avoid repetition and keep the code clean by passing parameters into the include component.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>For example, we’re going to create a <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">related_card.html</code> component that you can include at the end of your post. You will have to place the file inside <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">includes</code> directory. I usually create another folder called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">components</code> and group these components together.</p>

<p>Here is the structure of the directory:</p>
<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>_includes/
  components/
    related_card.html
  custom/
  footer.html
  head.html
  header.html
  main.html
  sidebar.html
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Here is the content of the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">related_card.html</code>.</p>

<div class="language-html highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>
<span class="nt">&lt;div</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"related_card"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;h4&gt;</span>{{ include.title }}<span class="nt">&lt;/h4&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;p&gt;</span>{{ include.description }}<span class="nt">&lt;/p&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;a</span> <span class="na">href=</span><span class="s">"{{ root_url }}{{ include.url }}"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Read More<span class="nt">&lt;/a&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/div&gt;</span>

</code></pre></div></div>

<p class="sidenote">You need to prepend <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">include</code> before each parameter because that’s how you will access these parameters later on.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-include-the-component">How to Include the Component</h2>

<p>If you’re using Jekyll for your blog, you will find a layout called <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">_post.html</code> that renders how a blog post should look. Here’s how you can include the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">related_card.html</code> and pass values into the component.</p>

<div class="language-html highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>
{% include components/related_card.html 
  title = "The Post Title"
  description = "Here is the description"
  url = "Here is the site URL"
%}

</code></pre></div></div>

<p>This approach is useful when you need to iterate through a collection, data or when you want to create an archive page with the card format as part of the layout. Here is how you can iterate all the posts on your site.</p>

<div class="language-html highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>
{% for post in site.posts %}
  {% include components/related_card.html 
    title = post.title
    description = post.description
    url = post.url
  %}
{% endif %}

</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Once you’ve familiarized yourself with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">include</code>, you can start removing some repetitive parts from your project and put them inside the components folder. You will be able to make changes without having to edit each page layout.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p><a href="https://jekyllrb.com/docs/includes/" title="Includes - Jekyll • Simple, blog-aware, static sites">Read the official documentation</a> to learn more what you can do with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">include</code>. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Set Default Window Size on Mac with Keyboard Maestro]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/default-window-size-keyboard-maestro/"/>
    <updated>2021-03-23T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/default-window-size-keyboard-maestro</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Resizing application windows is one of the easiest macros you can create with Keyboard Maestro. By implementing a single action, you can set a default window size for every application on your Mac. What if I tell you that there is a better way to organize and resize application windows?</p>

<p>With MacBook Pro, I often use the full-screen mode to take advantage of all the available screen states. After switching to iMac 27” as my main machine, I find that it requires more effort to organize the windows.</p>

<p>Rather than always viewing the application in full-screen mode, I set a default window size for each different group. I put the browser’s default window size (1440, 1000). Some of the productivity applications like Things and Finder are set to (960, 700).</p>

<p>The idea to build this macro came up when I was cleaning my Keyboard Maestro library. I found out that the “Resize and Center” macro I created a long time ago was <em>very inefficient</em>.</p>

<h2 id="the-old-resize-and-center-macro">The “Old” Resize and Center Macro</h2>

<p>The “Resize and Center” macro, available in the <strong>Global UI Control</strong> macro group, has only one task: to set the front window size to width to 1440 and height to 1000.</p>

<p class="sidenote">I have my reason to save the macro in the <strong>Global UI Control</strong> instead of creating a separate macro group for each application. It’s related to <a href="https://sayzlim.net/organize-keyboard-maestro-macros/" title="How I Organize Keyboard Maestro Macro Groups - Sayz Lim">how I organize my macro groups</a>.</p>

<p>Instead of assigning a global shortcut to the macro, I have to create a new macro group to selectively choose which applications to trigger the macro. For example, I can create a macro group called “Finder” and put an action to execute the “Resize and Center” macro in the group. <strong>The advantage of this approach is I can set a different type of trigger for each application</strong>, such as resizing the window whenever the application activates</p>

<p><a href="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/03/default-window-size-old-resize-macro.webp" title="Execute a Macro in a Separate Macro Group"> <img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/03/default-window-size-old-resize-macro.webp" alt="Execute a Macro in a Separate Macro Group" title="Execute a Macro in a Separate Macro Group" /> </a></p>

<p>There are some problems with this approach:</p>
<ol>
  <li>I have to create a new macro group for each application that uses the “Resize and Center” macro.</li>
  <li>I have to create a new “Resize and Center” for each different default window size.</li>
  <li>Using the “Trigger Macro by Name” action will show many duplicates of the “Resize and Center” macro.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="the-new-resize-and-center-macro">The “New” Resize and Center Macro</h2>

<p>Keyboard Maestro lets you pass parameters when executing a macro. By tweaking the “Resize and Center” macro, I can tell the new macro to accept width and height as the parameters to resize the window size dynamically.</p>

<p><a href="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/03/default-window-size-new-resize-macro.webp" title="&quot;New&quot; Resize and Center Macro"> <img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/03/default-window-size-new-resize-macro.webp" alt="&quot;New&quot; Resize and Center Macro" title="&quot;New&quot; Resize and Center Macro" /> </a></p>

<p>The macro is pretty straightforward. It accepts two parameters separated by a comma for width and height. You can access the parameter’s value respectively with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">%TriggerValue[1]%</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">%TriggerValue[2]%</code> and save them as local variables.</p>

<p class="sidenote">You can prepend <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Local</code> to the variable to prevent Keyboard Maestro from making the variable available globally for other macros. It’s one way to avoid clutter in the “variables” section under the preferences pane.</p>

<p>The remaining action is centering the front application window. I adjusted the vertical position to take into the menu bar height. Now, the “Resize and Center” macro can accept <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">(height, width)</code> as the parameter.</p>

<p class="sidenote">Click on the gear icon on the top right <strong>Execute Macro</strong> action to toggle <strong>With Parameter</strong> input fields.</p>

<h3 id="setting-multiple-default-sizes-with-switch-case">Setting Multiple Default Sizes with Switch Case</h3>

<p>Inside the “Global UI Control” macro group, I create a new macro called “Default Window Size”. I prefer to set <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">F8</code> as the hot key to trigger this macro and set the front window application to the default size. You can change it to your preferred shortcut.</p>

<p><a href="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/03/default-window-size-macro.webp" title="Default Window Size Macro"> <img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/03/default-window-size-macro.webp" alt="Default Window Size Macro" title="Default Window Size Macro" /> </a></p>

<p>The macro uses a <strong>Switch/Case Action</strong> to control the flow of the actions. It checks the front window application name — accessed through <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">%Application%1%</code> — by matching the regular expression through the term “Matches”.</p>

<p class="sidenote">Each application name is separated by a pipe for alternation. You can learn more about <a href="https://sayzlim.net/clipboards-regular-expression/" title="Manipulate Clipboards with Regular Expression - Sayz Lim">regular expressions in this post</a>.</p>

<p>The new macro offers much more versatility. I can easily set the default size for a new application by adding the application name into the matching expression. If I want to create a new default size, I just have to add another matching case in the control flow. If I want to change the window size, I just have to update the passing parameter value.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://s3.sayzlim.net/km/default-window-size.kmmacros" title="Download Default Window Size Macro">Download Default Window Size Macro</a></strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Evernote Device Limit Workaround]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/evernote-device-limit-workaround/"/>
    <updated>2021-03-16T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/evernote-device-limit-workaround</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most frustrating problems with Evernote Basic is that you can sign into the Evernote application up to only two devices. Here is a workaround that you can follow if you wish to use Evernote on more devices.</p>

<p>When <a href="https://mjtsai.com/blog/2020/11/13/evernote-goes-electron/">Evernote decided to go Electron</a>, I was under the impression that they need to <em>change</em> to streamline the product development. After all, we didn’t see many breakthroughs with the native application for years because they have different people working on each version of the application: Mac, Windows, iPhone, and Android.</p>

<p>The recent updates put off many existing paid customers. The Evernote web application butchered many features that paid customers used to love. I’ve seen many customers searching for Evernote replacement because of the device limitation. I’ve canceled Evernote Premium temporarily because I don’t feel the pricing justify for the features they offer.</p>

<p>As someone who owns iPhone and iPad, it’s easy to hit the limit early. I mostly spend my time working with MacBook Pro and iMac 27”, so I want to run Evernote as a separate application on these devices.</p>

<p>Fortunately,  I’ve found a way to turn the Evernote website into a full-fledged application running on macOS.</p>

<h2 id="building-evernote-desktop-with-nativefier">Building Evernote Desktop with Nativefier</h2>
<p>Since Evernote is built with Electron. There is no significant difference using Evernote on the website, desktop, or mobile devices. It also means that using Evernote with a browser doesn’t count towards your device limit.</p>

<p>All we have to do is to <em>package</em> the Evernote website into a native application that you can run as a separate entity from the desktop browsers. We’re going to use <a href="https://github.com/nativefier/nativefier" title="Nativefier: Make any web page a desktop application">Nativefier</a> in this tutorial.</p>

<p>If you haven’t installed Node.js, you will have to install it first on your machine. Check out this tutorial to <a href="https://sayzlim.net/setup-macos-web-development/" title="How to Set Up macOS for Web Development">set up a web development environment</a> correctly. Make sure you install the following tools:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Xcode Command Line Tools</li>
  <li>Homebrew</li>
  <li>Node.js</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/03/evernote-nativefier-terminal.webp" title="Installing Evernote with Nativefier"> <img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/03/evernote-nativefier-terminal.webp" alt="Installing Evernote with Nativefier" title="Installing Evernote with Nativefier" /> </a></p>

<p>Restart Terminal and switch to the latest version of Node.js. Copy and paste the following command into Terminal to install Nativefier.</p>

<div class="language-console highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="go">npm install -g nativefier
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<p>It may take a few minutes for the installation to complete. Once nativefier is installed, you can run the following command to create a native Evernote application from their official website.</p>

<div class="language-console highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="go">cd ~/Desktop &amp;&amp; nativefier --name 'Evernote' 'evernote.com'
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<p>The command above will create a folder containing the Evernote application built with Electron on the desktop. Move only <strong>Evernote.app</strong> into the Applications folder. You can delete the rest of the files in the folder.</p>

<h2 id="replacing-evernote-icon">Replacing Evernote Icon</h2>

<p><a href="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/03/evernote-nativefier-icon.webp" title="Evernote Icon Replacement"> <img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/03/evernote-nativefier-icon.webp" alt="Evernote Icon Replacement" title="Evernote Icon Replacement" /> </a></p>

<p>Pay attention that the Evernote application we built with Nativefier has Electron logo as the icon. This is expected because we didn’t pass any image into the command line when creating the application.</p>

<video controls="" style="max-width: 100%;">
<source src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/03/evernote-icon-replacement.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
</video>

<p>Here’s how you can update the Evernote icon you’ve just created:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Download your favorite Evernote icon from <a href="https://macosicons.com/evernote">macOSicons by Elias</a>.</li>
  <li>Right-click on the Evernote.app — located inside the Applications folder — and select “Get Info” from the contextual menu to display the info window.</li>
  <li>Drag the downloaded icon to the top of the Evernote.app icon inside the info window.</li>
</ol>

<p>You can open the Evernote application and sign in with your credentials. Now, Enjoy the native web version of Evernote without hitting the device limit set.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Replacing DragonDrop with Dropover]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/dropover-review/"/>
    <updated>2021-03-10T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/dropover-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been searching for a reliable DragonDrop replacement without any success. None of the alternatives were close to the workflow I needed: a quick way to drag and drop files into a holding bin that sits on top of the desktop. I’m glad that I found out about Dropover.</p>

<p>On the surface, Dropover works like DragonDrop. You select single or several files, and shake them to activate the shelf. You can place and hold these files inside the shelf, which you can use again in a different space. Check out the following video to see how it works.</p>

<video controls="" style="max-width: 100%;">
<source src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/03/dropover-demo.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
</video>

<h2 id="better-shelves">Better Shelves</h2>
<p>With DragonDrop, you’re limited to one shelf at a time. Dropover allows you to create several shelves that you can organize several files at once and move them to different destinations.</p>

<p>You may want to set the sensitivity to <strong>high</strong> because the default setting requires more shake to activate the shelf. I find myself using the <kbd>Shift</kbd> modifier more often these days.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/03/dropover-shelf-setting.webp" alt="Dropover Shelf Settings" title="Dropover Shelf Settings" /></p>

<h2 id="sharing-files-with-dropover-cloud">Sharing Files with Dropover Cloud</h2>
<p>On top of the core feature to hold files, you can also use their in-house Dropover Cloud to share them online. It comes with the feature to set a password and an expiration timer for the shared files.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/03/dropover-cloud-upload.webp" alt="Dropover Cloud Upload Screen" title="Dropover Cloud Upload Screen" /></p>

<p>Dropover offers a better integration to popular online file-sharing services like Dropbox, Google Drive, and One Drive. You can also share your files through <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT203093" title="Mail Drop limits - Apple Support">iCloud’s Mail Drop</a><sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<p>I don’t see Dropover replacing CleanShot X as my primary tool to share screenshots, but I will consider using it to share files online.</p>

<p>With all said, Dropover continues DragonDrop legacy as the best drag and drop macOS app to move files around.</p>

<p><a href="https://dropoverapp.com" title="Dropover ‐ Easier Drag and Drop on your Mac."><strong>Download Dropover</strong></a></p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Allowing users to share the file through Mail Drop is smart, but Apple does a poor job explaining how you can delete the shared files. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building a Plain HTML Form with ConvertKit]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/plain-html-form-convertkit/"/>
    <updated>2021-03-03T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/plain-html-form-convertkit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://convertkit.com" title="ConvertKit - Email Marketing for Online Creators">ConvertKit</a> provides different kinds of templates that creators can easily embed on their website, but as a result, it also comes with additional scripts and options you don’t need. I will show you how to create a lightweight form that you can integrate into your website.</p>

<p>Head over the Landing Pages and Forms to create a new form. Choose “Charlotte” as the design. Add another field and name it “First Name” if you want to collect your subscriber’s name. Choose “Embed” and “HTML” to view the content of the form.</p>

<p><img src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2021/03/plain-html-convertkit.webp" alt="Embed Using HTML with ConvertKit" title="Embed Using HTML with ConvertKit" /></p>

<p>You will need to locate the Form ID and User ID from the content of the HTML.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Form ID: The numerical values found in the URL while you’re editing the form. For example, mine is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">2056639</code>. You can also find it as an action value in the HTML as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">action="https://app.convertkit.com/forms/2056639/subscriptions"</code></li>
  <li>User ID: The unique string of your ID which is passed as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">data-uid</code> in the form. For example: <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">data-uid="c72f97e133"</code>.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="plain-html-convertkit-form">Plain HTML ConvertKit Form</h3>
<p>Here is the HTML ConvertKit form that you can integrate into your site. You have to replace the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">actions</code>, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">data-sv-form</code>, and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">data-uid</code> with your own values.</p>

<div class="language-html highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="nt">&lt;form</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"form"</span> <span class="na">action=</span><span class="s">"https://app.convertkit.com/forms/2056450/subscriptions"</span> <span class="na">method=</span><span class="s">"post"</span> <span class="na">data-sv-form=</span><span class="s">"2056450"</span> <span class="na">data-uid=</span><span class="s">"c249fe0755"</span> <span class="na">data-options=</span><span class="s">"{&amp;quot;settings&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;after_subscribe&amp;quot;:{&amp;quot;action&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;redirect&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;redirect_url&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;https://sayzlim.net/welcome/&amp;quot;}}}"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;label</span> <span class="na">for=</span><span class="s">"name"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>First Name<span class="nt">&lt;/label&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;input</span> <span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">"text"</span> <span class="na">value=</span><span class="s">""</span> <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">"fields[first_name]"</span> <span class="na">placeholder=</span><span class="s">"First Name"</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">"name"</span> <span class="na">required</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;label</span> <span class="na">for=</span><span class="s">"email"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>Email<span class="nt">&lt;/label&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;input</span> <span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">"email"</span> <span class="na">value=</span><span class="s">""</span> <span class="na">name=</span><span class="s">"email_address"</span> <span class="na">placeholder=</span><span class="s">"Email Address"</span> <span class="na">id=</span><span class="s">"email"</span> <span class="na">required</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
  <span class="nt">&lt;input</span> <span class="na">type=</span><span class="s">"submit"</span> <span class="na">data-element=</span><span class="s">"submit"</span> <span class="na">class=</span><span class="s">"subscribe"</span> <span class="na">value=</span><span class="s">"Subscribe"</span><span class="nt">&gt;</span>
<span class="nt">&lt;/form&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>In the default HTML template provided by ConvertKit, you will find <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">data-options</code> containing the value of options you can set for the form. Here is what it looks like if we display it as a JSON object.</p>

<div class="language-json highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
    </span><span class="nl">"settings"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="nl">"after_subscribe"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"action"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"message"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"success_message"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"Success! Now check your email to confirm your subscription."</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"redirect_url"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">""</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="p">},</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="nl">"analytics"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"google"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">null</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"facebook"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">null</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"segment"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">null</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"pinterest"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">null</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"sparkloop"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">null</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"googletagmanager"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">null</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="p">},</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="nl">"modal"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"trigger"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"timer"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"scroll_percentage"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">null</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"timer"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"devices"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"all"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"show_once_every"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="mi">15</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="p">},</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="nl">"powered_by"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"show"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">true</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"url"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"https://convertkit.com?utm_source=dynamic&amp;amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;amp;utm_campaign=poweredby&amp;amp;utm_content=form"</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="p">},</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="nl">"recaptcha"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"enabled"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">false</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="p">},</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="nl">"return_visitor"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"action"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"show"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"custom_content"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">""</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="p">},</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="nl">"slide_in"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"display_in"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"bottom_right"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"trigger"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"timer"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"scroll_percentage"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">null</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"timer"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"devices"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"all"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"show_once_every"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="mi">15</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="p">},</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="nl">"sticky_bar"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">{</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"display_in"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"top"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"trigger"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"timer"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"scroll_percentage"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="kc">null</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"timer"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="mi">5</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"devices"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"all"</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="w">
            </span><span class="nl">"show_once_every"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="mi">15</span><span class="w">
        </span><span class="p">}</span><span class="w">
    </span><span class="p">},</span><span class="w">
    </span><span class="nl">"version"</span><span class="p">:</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s2">"5"</span><span class="w">
</span><span class="p">}</span><span class="w">
</span></code></pre></div></div>

<p>Since you don’t need to pass most of the options above, we can keep the settings minimum by removing the values we don’t need.</p>

<p>The only option I enable is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">redirect_url</code>. It allows you to redirect subscribers to a custom landing page whenever they have successfully signed up for your newsletter. Replace <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">https://sayzlim.net/welcome/</code> with your landing page URL.</p>

<p>Once you’ve confirmed that the form is working, you can style it to match your site design.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tips for Using Things Efficiently on macOS]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/tips-using-things-macos/"/>
    <updated>2021-02-14T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/tips-using-things-macos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been using Things 3 as my GTD since 2014. It has become an essential part of my life. I want to share several tips for anyone looking to use Things to manage several aspects of your life. These tips are strictly for Things on macOS.</p>

<h2 id="1-use-keyboard-shortcuts-with-quick-entry">1. Use Keyboard Shortcuts with Quick Entry</h2>
<p>Quick Entry lets you jot down the tasks without bringing Things to the front. You should set it up if you haven’t done so. I assigned <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Control - Space</code> as the dedicated shortcut for this feature.</p>

<p>You can also add some details for the task by using the available shortcuts. Here are some default shortcuts I often use:</p>

<ul>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Command - S</code> to schedule the task to another date.</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Command - Shift - D</code> to set a deadline for the task.</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Command - Shift - M</code> to move the task into a different area or project.</li>
  <li><code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Command - Shift - T</code> to tag the task.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="2-its-okay-to-clutter-the-inbox">2. It’s Okay to Clutter The Inbox</h2>
<p>I used to be an extremely organized person. I couldn’t deal with a cluttered inbox at all. However, I realized the obsession with an empty inbox only crippled my productivity.</p>

<p>Inbox can be messy. Inbox doesn’t have to be empty.</p>

<p>Inbox is meant to be a temporary space for your tasks. You use it to collect tasks and ideas. If something comes up while you’re working, you can place them inside the Inbox.</p>

<h2 id="3-no-task-naming-rules">3. No Task Naming Rules</h2>
<p>You can name it however you want. Sometimes I just paste the link as the task name. Sometimes I leave the title blank and fill up only the details. You can rename them later.</p>

<p>There will be time for you to reorganize and remove those that are not important as you think.</p>

<h2 id="4-schedule-inbox-and-today-tasks">4. Schedule Inbox and Today Tasks</h2>
<p>Some tasks are not meant to be completed immediately. Review your Inbox and Today once in a few days and reschedule them if you’re overwhelmed by the number of tasks that show up in Today. Inbox can get massive if you don’t decide what you want to do with them. So, either delete or break them into smaller tasks by rescheduling them into another day.</p>

<p>That way, Today becomes more manageable because they’ve been spread out into different dates.</p>

<h2 id="5-use-deadline">5. Use Deadline</h2>
<p>The primary purpose of setting a deadline is to provide a state of urgency. If you have a task that must be completed before a specific date, you must select the due date a few days earlier for the task to appear in the Today view.</p>

<p>If you wish to learn more about Things, you should <a href="https://culturedcode.com/things/guide/">check out their official guide</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Find Conflicting Keyboard Shortcuts on Mac]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/find-conflicting-shortucts-mac/"/>
    <updated>2020-06-07T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/find-conflicting-shortucts-mac</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s frustrating to troubleshoot conflicting keyboard shortcuts on Mac because it doesn’t show you which app is currently binding the combination keys. Here’s how you can find the conflicting keys on Mac.</p>

<video controls="" style="max-width: 100%;">
<source src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2020/06/find-conflicting-shortcuts-mac.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
</video>

<p><a href="http://www.irradiatedsoftware.com/labs/" title="Irradiated Software - Labs - Beta Tested &bull; Gamma Blasted">ShortcutDetective</a> is a free app from Irradiated Labs that can help you detect conflicting shortcuts on your Mac. You can download ShortcutDetective and grant accessibility permission to start identifying the problematic keys combination.</p>

<p>The usage is straightforward. You press the shortcuts, and it will start to show you which macOS app is binding the keys.</p>

<p>It’s possible to <a href="/non-conflicting-shortcuts/" title="Non-Conflicting Shortcuts - Sayz Lim">avoid conflicting shortcuts</a> by following some best practices when assigning a shortcut.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quick Calculation Keyboard Maestro Macro]]></title>
    <link href="https://sayzlim.net/quick-calculation-keyboard-maestro-macro/"/>
    <updated>2020-05-27T00:00:00+07:00</updated>
    <id>https://sayzlim.net/quick-calculation-keyboard-maestro-macro</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Sometimes you want to quickly calculate a number while typing. Here’s how you can maintain the typing flow and calculate numbers with Keyboard Maestro.</p>

<p>We want the macro to replace the math formula with the result whenever we type the formula that ends with a question mark. Here are some examples:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>30*(50+20)?
100^2?
75*30?
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="macro-breakdown">Macro Breakdown</h2>

<video controls="" style="max-width: 100%;">
<source src="https://images.sayzlim.net/2020/05/quick-calculation-macro.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
</video>

<p>We’re going to select “This string is typed” as a trigger to decide when to call this macro. Change the dropdown to “regular expression match” and enter this expression:</p>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>[\d.,+\-*/()^]+\?
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>If you’re not familiar with regular expressions, you can <a href="https://sayzlim.net/clipboards-regular-expression/" title="Manipulate Clipboards with Regular Expression - Sayz Lim">learn more about it in this post</a>. What we’re doing here is to tell Keyboard Maestro:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Run the macro only when any digit <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\d</code> and math signs like <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">+\-*/()^</code> appear at least once and repeat regardless of the order. You can see that we wrapped these values in a bracket as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">[\d.,+\-*/()^]+</code> followed by a plus sign.</li>
  <li>Run the macro only when the matched string ends with a question mark <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">\?</code>.</li>
  <li>The backslash is used to escape special characters in regular expressions such as question mark, plus, and minus sign.</li>
</ul>

<p>The triggered macro will copy the selected line and extract only the detected math formula. It will remove the question mark and pass it to <strong>Filter Variable “Formula” with Calculate</strong> and save the result back to <strong>Formula</strong> variable.</p>

<p>In the last step, the macro replaces the detected formula in the clipboard with the result and then paste it back to the application source.</p>

<p>There are some lessons to build a macro here. You can extract strings with regular expressions, manipulate them, and send them back to the source.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://s3.sayzlim.net/f/km-automatic-calculation.zip">Download Quick Calculation Macro</a></strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
